<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                 "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % sharedents SYSTEM "shared-entities.xml" >
%sharedents;
]>

<book id="dCacheBook"
      xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">

  <title>The dCache Book</title>
  <subtitle>for &dcache-version;-series (&layout-current; layout)</subtitle>
  <titleabbrev>dCache Book</titleabbrev>

  <bookinfo>
    <abstract>
      <para>
	The &dcache; Book is the guide for administrators of &dcache;
	systems. The first part describes the installation of a simple
	single-host &dcache; instance. The second part describes the
	components of &dcache; and in what ways they can be
	configured. This is the place for finding information about
	the role and functionality of components in &dcache; as needed
	by an administrator. The third part contains solutions for
	several problems and tasks which might occur during operating
	of a &dcache; system. Finally, the last two parts contain a
	glossary and a parameter and command reference.
      </para>

    </abstract>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
	<imagedata fileref="images/dCache-book-logo.svg"
		   format="SVG" align="center" contentwidth="10cm"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject role="fo">
	<imagedata fileref="images/logos-emi-helmholtz.svg"
		   format="SVG" align="center" contentwidth="13cm"/>
      </imageobject>
      <textobject role="fo">
	<phrase>EMI</phrase>
      </textobject>
      <caption role="fo">
	<para>
	  This work is co-funded by the European Commission as part of
	  the EMI project under Grant Agreement INFSO-RI-261611.
	</para>
	<para>
	  EMI-Product: dCache-server; Version: &dcache-version;
	</para>
      </caption>

   </mediaobject>

  </bookinfo>

  <preface>
    <title>Preface</title>

    <para> Welcome to the &dcache;. &dcache; is a distributed storage solution for storing huge
      amounts of data without a hard limit, used to provide storage in the petabyte range. Therefore it qualifies
      as the storage system supporting data intensive experiments.
    </para>

    <para>
      &dcache; is a joined effort between the Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron (DESY)
      in Hamburg, Nordic Data Grid Facility (NDGF based in Copenhagen), the Fermi National Accelerator Laboratory near Chicago
      with significant distributions and support from the University of California, San
      Diego, INFN, Bari as well as Rutherford Appleton Laboratory, UK and CERN in Geneva.
    </para>

    <para>
      &dcache; can use hierarchical storage management (e.g., hard disk and tape), provides
      mechanisms to automatically increase performance and balance loads, increase resilience
      and availability. It also supplies advanced control systems to manage data as well as data
      flows. Normal filesystem (btrfs, ext4, XFS, ZFS) is used to store data on storage nodes.

      There are several ways of accessing data stored in &dcache;:

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>&nfs; 4.1 (&chimera;)</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>&http; and &webdav; </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>&gridftp; (&gsiftp;)</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>xrootd</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>&srm; (versions 1.1 and 2.2) </para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>&dcap; and &gsidcap; </para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

      &dcache; supports certificate based authentication through the Grid Security Infrastructure
      used in &gsiftp;, &gsidcap; transfer protocols and  the &srm; management protocol.
      Certificate authentication is also available for &http; and &webdav;.

      &dcache; also supports fine-grain authorization with support for POSIX file permissions
      and &nfs;-style access control lists.

      Other features of &dcache; are:
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem><para>Resilience and high availability can be implemented in different ways by having multiple replicas of the same files.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Easy migration of data via the migration module.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>A powerful cost calculation system that allows to control the data flow (reading and writing from/to pools, between pools and also between pools and tape).</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Load balancing and performance tuning by hot pool replication (via cost calculation and replicas created by pool-to-pool-transfers).</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Space management and support for space tokens.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Garbage collection of replicas, depending on their flags, age, et cetera.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Detailed logging and debugging as well as accounting and statistics.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>&xml; information provider with detailed live information about the cluster.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Scriptable adminstration interface with a terminal-based front-end.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Web-interface with live information of the most important information.</para></listitem>
        <listitem><para>Ensuring data integrity through checksumming.</para></listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

    </para>

    <para>
      &dcache; / &srm; can transparently manage data distributed among
      dozens of disk storage nodes (sometimes distributes over several countries).
      The system has shown to significantly improve the efficiency of connected tape storage
      systems, by caching, gather and flush and scheduled staging techniques.
      Furthermore, it optimizes the throughput to and from data clients by dynamically
      replicating datasets on the detection of load hot spots. The system
      is tolerant against failures of its data servers, which allows administrators
      to deploy commodity disk storage components.
    </para>

    <para>
      Access to the data is provided by various standard protocols. Furthermore
      the software comes with an implementation of the Storage Resource Manager
      protocol (&srm;), which is an open standard for grid middleware
      to communicate with site specific storage fabrics.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Who should read this book?</title>
      <para>This book is primerally targeted at system administrators.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Minimum System Requirements?</title>
      <para>
        For minimal test installation:
        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>Hardware: contemporary CPU , 1 GiB of RAM , 100 MiB free harddisk space</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Software: Oracle/Sun Java, Postgres SQL Server</para></listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </para>
      <para>
        For a high performance Grid scenario the hardware requirements highly differ, which
        makes it impossible to provide such parameters here. However, if you wish to setup a
        &dcache;-based storage system, just let us know and we will help you with your system
        specifications. Just contact us: <email>support@dcache.org</email>.
      </para>
    </section>


    <section>


      <title>What is inside?</title>

      <para>
        This book shall introduce you to &dcache; and provide you with the details of the installation.
        It describes configuration, customization of &dcache; as well as the usage of several protocols
        that &dcache; supports. Additionally, it provides cookbooks for standard tasks.
      </para>

      <para>
        Here is an overview part by part:
      </para>

      <para>
        Part 1, Getting started:
        This part introduces you to the cells and domain concept in &dcache;. It provides a detailed
        description of installing, the basic configuration, and upgrading &dcache;.
      </para>

      <para>
        Part 2, Configuration of dCache:
        Within this part the configuration of several additional features of &dcache; is described.
        They are not necessary to run &dcache; but will be needed by some users depending on
        their requirements.
      </para>

      <para>
        Part 3, Cookbook: This part comprises guides for specific tasks a system
        administrator might want to perform.
      </para>

    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Looking for help?</title>
      <para>This part gets you all the help that you might need:</para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>For acquiring resources:
            <itemizedlist>
	      <listitem>
		<para>
		  The <ulink
		  url="http://www.dcache.org/downloads">download
		  page</ulink>.
		</para>
	      </listitem>
              <listitem>
		<para>
		  The <ulink
		  url="http://trac.dcache.org/projects/dcache/wiki/manuals/Yum">YUM
		  repositories</ulink>.
		</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist>
          </para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>For getting help during installation: </para>
          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>Developers <email>support@dcache.org</email></para></listitem>
            <listitem>
              <para>
                Additional Support:
                <itemizedlist>
                  <listitem><para>German support:<email>german-support@dcache.org</email></para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>UK support:<email>GRIDPP-STORAGE@JISCMAIL.AC.UK</email></para></listitem>
		  <listitem><para>USA support:<email>osg-storage@opensciencegrid.org</email></para></listitem>
                  <listitem><para>User Forum: <email>user-forum@dcache.org</email></para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>
              </para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            For features that you would like to see in &dcache; or bugs that should be fixed:
            Just write an e-mail to <email>support@dcache.org</email>
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <!--listitem>
          <para>
            For general questions that you might want to ask: Just use the new
            comment feature under the respective section in the book. This will be available from 01.01.2011.
          </para>
        </listitem-->
        <listitem>
          <para>
            If you like to stay up-to-date about new releases you can use the RSS feeds available from
	    <ulink url="http://www.dcache.org/downloads">our downloads page</ulink>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            For EMI releases of &dcache; please visit the <ulink
            url="http://www.eu-emi.eu/releases">EMI
            &dcache; download page</ulink>.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>


    </section>

  </preface>

  <toc/>

  <xi:include href="start.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="config.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="cookbook.xml"/>
  <xi:include href="reference.xml"/>

</book>
