<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">     

<chapter id="cf-hopping">

  <title>File Hopping</title>
  <partauthors>Patrick Fuhrmann</partauthors>
  
  <para>
    File hopping is a collective term in dCache, summarizing 
    the possibilty of having files being transferred
    between dCache pools triggered by a variety of conditions.
    Most of the features described here will be available starting
    with dCache release 1.6.7. The most prominent examples are :
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        If a file is requested by a client but the file resides on a pool
        from which this client, by configuration, is not allowed to read data,
        the dataset is transferred to an 'allowed' pool first.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        If a dCache pool encounters a steady high load, the system may,
        if configured, decide to replicate files to other pools to achieve
        an equal load distribution.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        HSM restore operations may be split into two steps. The first one reads
        data from tertiary storage to an 'HSM connected' pool and the second step
        takes care that the file is replicated to a general read pool. Under some
        conditions this separation of HSM and non HSM pools might become necessary
        for performance reasons.
        </para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        If a dataset has been written into dCache it might become necessary
        to have this file replicated instantly. The reasons can be, to either 
        have a second, safe copy, or to make sure that clients don't access the file for reading
        on the write pools. 
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </para>
  <section id="cf-hopping-config">
  <title>File Hopping by configuration</title>
    <para>
       
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="cf-hopping-hotspot">
  <title>File Hopping by hot spot detection</title>
    <para>

    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="cf-hopping-hsm-restore">
  <title>File Hopping after restore from tertiary storage</title>
    <para>

    </para>
  </section>
  <section id="cf-hopping-onarrival">
  <title>File Hopping after on arrival from outside dCache</title>
    <para>

    </para>
  </section>
 
</chapter>
