<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % sharedents SYSTEM "shared-entities.xml" >
%sharedents;

<!ENTITY rdbms "<acronym>RDBMS</acronym>">
]>

<chapter id="cf-alarms">
  <title>The &serv-alarms; Service</title>
  <para>
    &dcache; has an &serv-alarms; service which records errors
    (<firstterm>alarms</firstterm>) requiring more or less urgent intervention.
    The webadmin servlet running inside the &serv-httpd; service has a special
    page for querying, displaying and tracking these alarms.
    There is also an option for sending alarm notifications via email.
    The alarms data can be stored either in an &xml; file or in
    a database. The alarms service is turned off by default.
  </para>
  <section id='cf-alarms-basic'>
    <title>The Basic Setup</title>
    <para>
      It is not necessary to run the &serv-alarms; service in a separate domain,
      though depending on the individual system configuration it may still be advisable
      not to embed the service in a domain already burdened with higher memory
      requirements.  To handle alarms under a relatively high load
      (100Hz on the server end) requires only about 2% more of the cpu,
      but about 75-100 MiB of additional space.  In order to
      capture any alarms from other domains at startup, it is also
      necessary to arrange for the alarm service to start before the other
      doors and pools.
    </para>
    <para>
      While there is nothing strictly preventing the use of multiple &serv-alarms;
      services, under normal circumstances this should not be necessary.
      The only constraint on the service set-up has to do with the
      storage option.  Unlike for the &rdbms; (relational database) back-end,
      there is currently no option for remote access of the &xml; file.
      Since the alarms storage needs to be written to by the &serv-alarms;
      service but also read by the &serv-httpd; service, it is thus necessary
      for that file to exist on a shared or mounted partition visible to both.
      Obviously, no such requirement exists for the &rdbms; option.
    </para>
    <para>
      Add the &serv-alarms; service to a domain in the layout file:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
    [alarmsDomain]
    [alarmsDomain/alarms]
    alarms.db.type=rdbms
    ...
    </programlisting>
    <para>
      OR
    </para>
    <programlisting>
    [someotherDomain]
    [someotherDomain/alarms]
    alarms.db.type=rdbms
    [someotherDomain/someotherservice]
    ...
    </programlisting>
    <para>
    Note that the storage type setting <varname>alarms.db.type</varname>
    must be defined either in the layout or <filename>&path-ode-ed;/dcache.conf</filename>
    file because its default value is <literal>off</literal>; this can be set to
    either <literal>xml</literal>, or <literal>rdbms</literal>.  In the latter
    case, the standard set of properties can be used to configure the connection
    url, db user, and so forth.  Before using the <literal>rdbms</literal>
    option for the first time, be sure to run:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
        createdb -U <varname>alarms.db.user</varname> alarms
    </programlisting>
    <para>
    to create the database; as usual, the actual schema will be initialized
    automatically when the service is started.
    </para>
    <para>
    For the &xml; option, the storage file is usually found in the shared directory
    for alarms (corresponding to <varname>alarms.dir</varname>); the usual path is
    <filename>&path-od-vld;/store.xml</filename>, but the location can be changed by setting
    <varname>alarms.db.xml.path</varname>. This  will automatically be propagated
    to <varname>alarms.db.url</varname> and consequently to
    <varname>httpd.alarms.db.url</varname> if the two domains are on the same
    host; if they are not (and share this file path via a mount, for instance),
    be sure to set the httpd property in the layout or
    <filename>&path-ode-ed;/dcache.conf</filename> on the httpd host to
    correspond to the new <varname>alarms.db.url</varname>.
    </para>
    <para>
    As a rule of thumb, the choice between &xml; and &rdbms; is dictated by two
    factors:  whether it is feasible to share the &xml; file between the
    two services as noted, and how much history is to be preserved.
    While the &xml; option is more lightweight and easier to configure,
    it is limited by performance, experiencing considerable read and write
    slowdown as the file fills (beyond 1000 entries or so). If you do not
    need to maintain records of alarms (and either manually delete alarms
    which have been serviced, or use the built-in cleanup feature – see below),
    then this option should be sufficient.  Otherwise, the extra steps of
    installing postgreSQL on the appropriate node and creating the alarms
    database (as above) may be worth the effort.
    </para>
    <section id='cf-alarms-basic-remoteConfiguration'>
      <title>Configure where the &serv-alarms; service is Running</title>
    <para>
    The alarms infrastructure is actually a wrapper around the logging
    layer and makes use of a simple tcp socket logger to transmit logging events
    to the server.  In each domain, the <filename>&path-ode-ed;/logback.xml</filename>
    configuration references the following properties to control remote logging:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
        dcache.log.level.remote=off
        dcache.log.server.host=localhost
        dcache.log.server.port=9867
    </programlisting>
    <para>
    As with the &serv-alarms; service database type, remote logging is
    turned off by default.  Under normal circumstances it should be
    sufficient to set this to <literal>error</literal> in order to receive alarms.
    All internally generated alarms (see below) are in fact guaranteed to
    be sent at this logging level. Remote transmission of events at lower
    logging levels is possible, but caution should be taken inasmuch anything
    below <literal>warn</literal> significantly increases network traffic
    and could risk overloading the server or creating a bottleneck.
    This service was not designed to provide robust centralized debugging.
    </para>
    <para>
    If all of your &dcache; domains run on the same host, then the
    default (<literal>localhost</literal> value will work. But usually your
    &dcache; will not be configured to run on a single node, so each node will
    need to know the destination of the remote logging events.  On all the nodes
    except where the actual &serv-alarms; service resides, you will thus need to
    modify the <filename>&path-ode-ed;/dcache.conf</filename> file or the
    layout file to set the <varname>dcache.log.server.host</varname>
    property (and restart &dcache; if it is already up).  The default
    port should usually not need to be modified; in any case, it
    needs to correspond to whatever port the service is running on.  From
    inspection of the <filename>&path-ods-usd;/alarms.properties</filename> file, you
    can see that the alarms-specific properties mirror the logger properties:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
     #  ---- Host on which this service is running
     alarms.net.host=${dcache.log.server.host}
     #  ---- TCP port the alarms service listens on
     alarms.net.port=${dcache.log.server.port}
    </programlisting>
    <para>
    The first property should not need any adjustment, but if
    <varname>alarms.net.port</varname> is modified, be sure to modify the
    <varname>dcache.log.server.port</varname> property on the other nodes to
    correspond to it.  In general, it is advisable to work directly with the
    <varname>dcache.log.server</varname> properties everywhere.
    </para>
    <informalexample>
	<para>
	  An example of a &dcache; which consists of a head
	  node, some door nodes and some pool nodes. Assume that the
	  &serv-httpd; service and the &serv-alarms; service are
	  running on the head node. Then you would need to set the
	  property <varname>dcache.log.server.host</varname> on the pool
	  nodes and on the door nodes to the host on which the
	  &serv-alarms; service is running.
	</para>
	   <programlisting>
            dcache.log.server.host=<replaceable>head-node</replaceable>
       </programlisting>
    </informalexample>
    </section>
    <section id='cf-alarms-basic-alarmTypes'>
      <title>Types of Alarms</title>
    <para>
    As stated previously, the &dcache; alarm system runs on top of
    the logging system (and more specifically, depends on the
    <literal>ch.qos.logback</literal> logging library).  It promotes
    normal logging events to alarm status in one of two ways.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>BUILT-IN (MARKED) ALARMS</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Some alarms are already coded into dCache.  These bear the
        general logging marker <literal>ALARM</literal> and also
        can carry sub-markers for type and uniqueness identifiers. They
        also carry information indicating the host, domain
        and service which emits them.  All such alarms are logged at
        the ERROR event level.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>SERVER-SIDE (OPTIONAL) ALARMS</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Logging events which arrive at the alarm server, but which do
        not carry a specific alarm type marker (these may be events
        at any logging level, not just ERROR), can nevertheless be redefined
        as a specific type of alarm via a set of filters provided by
        the administrator.  These filters or custom alarm definitions
        reside in a special &xml; file usually written to the alarms space.
        Further explanation as to how to create such filters is given
        in another section below.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </section>
    <section id='cf-alarms-Priority'>
    <title>Alarm Priority</title>
    <para>
    The notion of alarm or alert carries the implication that
    this particular error or condition requires user attention/intervention;
    there may be, however, differences in urgency which permit the ordering of
    such notices in terms of degree of importance.  &dcache; allows the
    administrator complete control over this prioritization.
    </para>
    <para>
    The available priority levels are:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <literal>CRITICAL</literal>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <literal>HIGH</literal>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <literal>MODERATE</literal>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <literal>LOW</literal>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
    Any alarm can be set to whatever priority level is deemed appropriate.
    This can be done through the admin interface commands (see below).
    Without any customization, all alarms (of both types) are given a
    default priority level.  This level can be changed via the value of
    <variable>alarms.priority-mapping.default</variable>, which by default
    is <literal>critical</literal>.
    </para>
    <para>
    Filtering based on priority is possible both in the webadmin page (see below),
    and for alarms sent via email (<variable>alarms.email.threshold</variable>;
    fuller discussion of how to enable email alarms is given in a later section).
    </para>
    <note>
    There also exists the possibility of filtering out only alarms from the main
    database into a separate log file.  This option is enabled using
    <variable>alarms.enable.history</variable>, and similarly has a priority
    threshold, <variable>alarms.history.threshold</variable>.  This is
    particularly useful in tandem with the &xml; storage option; it allows
    preservation of a condensed record of the alarms even after their full
    entries have been deleted from the database.
    </note>
    </section>
    <section id='cf-alarms-toolsShell'>
    <title>Working with Alarms: Shell Commands</title>
    <para>
    Some basic alarm commands are available as part of the dCache shell.
    The following is an abbreviated description; for fuller information,
    see the dCache man page.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>alarm send</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Send an  arbitrary  alarm  message  to  the  alarm  server.
        The remote server address is taken from the local values for
        <variable>dcache.log.server.host</variable> and
        <variable>dcache.log.server.port</variable>. If the [-t=TYPE] option
        is used, it must be a predefined (internal) alarm type.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>alarm list</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
         Displays a list of all alarm types currently defined in dCache code
         (i.e., predefined, internal types).  Since these types can be
         modified with any incremental release, a listing in this
         manual would be of limited value.  It is easy enough to
         check which ones currently are defined using this command,
         the <literal>predefined ls</literal> admin command, or the auto-completing
         <literal>Alarm Type</literal> combo box on the webadmin alarms page.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>alarm [add | modify | remove]</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
         Activates an interpreter for adding, modifying or removing a filter
         definition.  The interpreter walks you through the steps and
         choices.  The results are written to the definitions file given by
         the local value for <variable>alarms.custom-definitions.path</variable>.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    </section>
    <section id='cf-alarms-toolsAdmin'>
    <title>Working with Alarms: Admin Commands</title>
    <para>
    A similar set of commands is available through the admin interface.
    To see fuller information for each of these, do <literal>help [command]</literal>.
    </para>
    <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>definition add [OPTIONS]</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Add a new custom definition; if a definition of this type already exists,
        the new definition will overwrite it.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>definition keywords</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Print the list of attribute names whose values can be used as keyword
        identifiers for the alarm.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>definition ls [type]</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Print a single definition or sorted list of definitions.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>definition reload [path]</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Reinitialize the definitions from the saved changes.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>definition rm type</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Remove the existing alarm definition.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>definition save [path]</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Save the current definitions to persistent back-up.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>definition set type name value </literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Set the attribute of an existing alarm definition.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>definition unset type name </literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Unset (remove) the attribute of an existing alarm definition.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>predefined ls</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Print a list of all internally defined alarms.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>priority get default</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Get the current default alarm priority value.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>priority ls [type]</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Print a single priority level or sorted list of priority levels for all
        known alarms.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>priority reload [path]</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Reinitialize priority mappings from saved changes.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>priority restore all</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Set all defined alarms to the current default priority value.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>priority save [path]</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Save the current priority mappings to persistent back-up.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>priority set type low|moderate|high|critical</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Set the priority of the alarm type.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>priority set default low|moderate|high|critical</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Set the default alarm priority value.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>send [OPTIONS] message</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Send an alarm to the alarm service.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <note>
    Custom definitions and priority mappings are backed by files corresponding
    to the properties <variable>alarms.custom-definitions.path</variable>
    and <variable>alarms.priority-mapping.path</variable>, respectively.  It
    is always possible to modify these files directly by hand. These by default
    are mapped to <filename>&path-od-vld;/alarms.custom-definitions.xml</filename>
    and <filename>&path-od-vld;/alarms-priority.properties</filename>. In order
    for the changes to take effect, either restart the alarms domain, or
    use the respective <literal>reload</literal> admin command.  It should be
    understood that when using the admin commands, any modifications are done in
    memory only and are not flushed automatically to the underlying file,
    so any permanent changes need to be made via the <literal>save</literal>
    command.
    </note>
    <note>
    It is possible to change the file locations by setting the above-mentioned
    properties in the layout or <filename>&path-ode-ed;/dcache.conf</filename>.
    As can be seen from the admin commands, it is also possible to specify the
    path as an option on the respective <literal>save</literal> and
    <literal>reload</literal> commands.  Note, however, that this is meant
    mainly for temporary or back-up purposes, as the path defined in the local
    dcache configuration will remain unaltered after that command
    completes and the priority map or definitions will be reloaded from there
    once again whenever the domain is restarted.
    </note>
    <note>
    Any changes made via the <literal>priority set default</literal> command
    are in-memory only.  To change this default permanently, set the
    <variable>alarms.priority-mapping.default</variable> property
    in the layout or <filename>&path-ode-ed;/dcache.conf</filename>.
    </note>
    </section>
    <section id='cf-alarms-toolsWebadmin'>
    <title>Working with Alarms: The Webadmin Alarms Page</title>
    </section>
    <para>
      The Alarms Web Page is an admin page and thus requires authentication. You
      must enable &https; and set an admin gid (0 by default):
    </para>
    <note>
      <para>
	   For the authenticated mode you need to generate a pk12 hostcert for
       SSL. This can be done by running the dcache command:
       <literal>import hostcert [--hostcert=FILE] [--hostkey=FILE] [--out=FILE] [--password=PASSWORD]</literal>
       after obtaining a hostcert and hostkey, which are by default placed in
       <filename>/etc/grid-security</filename>.
      </para>
    </note>
    <programlisting>
    [httpdDomain]
        httpd.enable.authn=true
        httpd.authz.admin-gid=<replaceable>1234</replaceable>
    [httpdDomain/httpd]
    </programlisting>
    <informalfigure id="fig-alarms-webpage">
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject role="fo">
	           <imagedata fileref="images/Alarms.png" format="PNG" align="center" contentwidth="16cm"/>
               <!-- width="100%" scalefit="1" contentdepth="100%" should scale optimally,
                    but fop doesnt like it -->
            </imageobject>
            <imageobject role="html">
	           <imagedata fileref="/images/Alarms.png" format="PNG" align="center" width="100%"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </informalfigure>
    <orderedlist numeration='upperalpha' >
    <listitem>
    The QUERY FILTER form can be used to limit the display of
    alarms in the table. The underlying query to the database is
    based on whether the entry has been marked as an alarm (the radio buttons
    indicating undefined, yes and no, respectively), the time interval
    in which to search, the <literal>alarm type</literal>, and the result
    range; these are marked by 'D' on the example screenshot above. The date
    referred to in <literal>after</literal> and <literal>before</literal>
    is that of the latest update to that entry, not the timestamp of its
    original arrival. Each click of the <literal>Refresh</literal>
    button will reload the data from the database based on these parameters.
    The default behavior is ALL ALARMS ONLY (unspecified type or range).
    Placing a single date in the Beginning box will give you all entries from
    that date up to today (inclusive); a single date in the Ending box will
    give all entries up to that date (inclusive).  The other options,
    marked by 'M', all do in-memory filtering.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    The <literal>Priority</literal> choice works
    like a debugging level, such that choosing <literal>MODERATE</literal>
    will expose all alarms of that priority or above, thus including
    <literal>HIGH</literal> and <literal>CRITICAL</literal>, but excluding
    <literal>LOW</literal>.  Note that non-alarms are unaffected by this
    setting.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
	The <literal>Match Expression</literal> filters by
	appending all fields to a single string and searching for a matching
	substring. If the <literal>Regular Expression</literal> box
	is checked, the expression to match is compiled as a (Java) regex.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
	The header of the result table contains two checkboxes which allow
	you to check or uncheck the respective columns for all
	displayed items. Checking <literal>Delete</literal> and then
	clicking <literal>Refresh</literal> will actually eliminate
	the entry from persistent store.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
	<literal>Closed</literal> is a way of marking the alarm as
	having been dealt with while maintaining a record of it. The
	<literal>Show Closed Alarms</literal> checkbox allows you to
	display them (turned off by default).
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
    All column titles appearing in white can be clicked to sort
    the table by that column.  While there is no column indicating
    alarm priority (as this attribute is external to the alarm schema),
    alarms are sorted by priority first.  Non-alarms follow alarms.
    If both alarms and non-alarms are displayed, alarms are colored
    dark red.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
	<literal>Notes</literal> is an editable field to be used for
	any special remarks.
    </listitem>
    </orderedlist>
    <para>
      When <literal>Refresh</literal> is clicked, any updates to
      <literal>Closed</literal> and <literal>Notes</literal> are first
      saved, then any <literal>Deletes</literal> are processed, and
      finally, the table is repopulated using the current query
      filter. The entire form is set to auto-refresh every 60 seconds.
    </para>
  </section>
  <section id='cf-alarms-cleanup'>
  <title>Advanced Service Configuration:  Enabling Automatic Cleanup</title>
    <para>
      An additional feature of the alarms infrastructure is automatic
      cleanup of processed alarms. An internal thread runs every so
      often, and purges all alarms marked as <literal>closed</literal>
      with a timestamp earlier than the given window. This daemon can
      be configured using the properties
      <varname>alarms.enable.cleaner</varname>,
      <varname>alarms.cleaner.timeout</varname>,
      <varname>alarms.cleaner.timeout.unit</varname>,
      <varname>alarms.cleaner.delete-entries-before</varname> and
      <varname>alarms.cleaner.delete-entries-before.unit</varname>.  The
      cleaner is off by default.  This feature is mainly useful when running
      over an &xml; store, to mitigate slow-down due to bloat; nevertheless,
      there is nothing prohibiting its use with &rdbms;.
    </para>
  </section>
    <section id='cf-alarms-email'>
    <title>Advanced Service Configuration:  Enabling Email Alerts</title>
    <para>
    To configure the server to send alarms via email, you need to set
    a series of alarm properties.  No changes are necessary to any
    <filename>logback.xml</filename> file.  The most important properties:
    </para>
    <variablelist>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>alarms.enable.email, alarms.email.threshold</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Off (false) and <literal>critical</literal> by default.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>alarms.email.smtp-host, alarms.email.smtp-port</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Email server destination.  The port defaults to 25.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>SMTP authentication and encryption</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        The SMTP client used by dCache supports authentication via plain
        user passwords as well as both the STARTTLS and SSL protocols.
        Note that STARTTLS differs from SSL in that, in STARTTLS,
        the connection is initially non-encrypted and only after the
        STARTTLS command is issued by the client (if the server supports it)
        does the connection switch to SSL. In SSL mode, the connection is
        encrypted right from the start. Which of these to use is usually
        determined by the server.
        </para>
        <para>
        If username and password are left undefined, unauthenticated sends
        will be attempted, which may not be supported by the server.
        </para>
        <para>
        The values to use for plain user/password authentication default
        to undefined. NOTE:  while using SSL will guarantee encryption
        over the wire, there is currently no way of storing an encrypted
        password.
        Two possible workarounds:
            a.  Set up an admin account with a plaintext password that
                is protected by root privileges but which can be shared among
                adminstrators or those with access to the host containing this
                file;
            b.  Set up a host-based authentication to the server; the email
                admin will usually require the client IP, and it will need
                to be static in that case.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    <varlistentry>
      <term><literal>sender and recipient</literal></term>
      <listitem>
        <para>
        Only one sender may be listed, but multiple recipients can be indicated
        by a comma-separated list of email addresses.
        </para>
      </listitem>
    </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    <para>
    See the shared defaults <filename>&path-ods-usd;/alarms.properties</filename> file
    for additional settings.
    </para>
    </section>
    <section id='cf-alarms-Definitions'>
    <title>Advanced Service Configuration:  Custom Alarm Definitions</title>
    <para>
    It should be fairly straightforward to add or modify custom definitions
    via either the interpreter from the dcache shell, or the admin
    <literal>definition</literal> commands.
    </para>
    <para>
    An alarm definition consists of the following:
    </para>
    <informaltable tabstyle='small' frame='all'>
    <tgroup cols='3' align='left'>
        <colspec colwidth='*'/>
        <colspec colwidth='2*'/>
        <colspec colwidth='*'/>
    <thead>
        <row><entry>Property</entry>
             <entry>Possible values</entry>
             <entry>Required</entry></row>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    <row>
      <entry><varname>type</varname></entry>
      <entry>Name of this alarm type (settable only once).</entry>
      <entry><literal>YES</literal></entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry><varname>keyWords</varname></entry>
      <entry>Whitespace-delimited concatenation of key field names (see below).</entry>
      <entry><literal>YES</literal></entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry><varname>regex</varname></entry>
      <entry>A pattern to match the message with.
      <note>
        It is advisable to place the regex pattern in double
        quotes, e.g., "[=].[\w]*"
      </note>
      </entry>
      <entry><literal>YES</literal></entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry><varname>regex-flags</varname></entry>
      <entry>A string representation of the (Java) regex flags options,
      joined by the 'or' pipe symbol: e.g.,
      <literal>CASE_INSENSITIVE | DOTALL</literal>. For fuller
      explanation, see the Java Tutorial on <ulink
      url="http://docs.oracle.com/javase/tutorial/essential/regex">Regular
      Expressions</ulink>.</entry>
      <entry><literal>NO</literal></entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry><varname>match-exception</varname></entry>
      <entry>&true; = recur over embedded exception messages
      when applying the regex match (default is &false;).</entry>
      <entry><literal>NO</literal></entry>
    </row>
    <row>
      <entry><varname>depth</varname></entry>
      <entry>Integer &ge; 0, = depth of exception trace to examine when
      applying match-exception; undefined means unbounded (default).</entry>
      <entry><literal>NO</literal></entry>
    </row>
    </tbody>
    </tgroup>
    </informaltable>
    <para>
    For example:
    </para>
    <programlisting>
      <literal>&lt;alarmType</literal>&gt;
      <literal>&lt;type</literal>&gt;SERVICE_CREATION_FAILURE<literal>&lt;/type</literal>&gt;
      <literal>&lt;regex</literal>&gt;(.+) from ac_create<literal>&lt;/regex</literal>&gt;
      <literal>&lt;keyWords</literal>&gt;group1 type host domain service<literal>&lt;/keyWords</literal>&gt;
      <literal>&lt;/alarmType</literal>&gt;
    </programlisting>
    <para>
      The alarm key (the property <varname>keyWords</varname>) is
      the set of attributes whose values uniquely identify the alarm
      instance. For example, an alarm defined using <literal>message</literal>,
      but without including <literal>timestamp</literal> in its key,
      would suggest that all events with exactly the same message content are
      to be considered duplicates of the first such alarm. The key field names
      which can be used to constitute the key include the attributes defined
      for all alarms, plus the parsing of the message field into regex groups:
    </para>
    <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
            <literal>timestamp</literal>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <literal>domain</literal>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <literal>service</literal>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <literal>host</literal>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <literal>message (= group0)</literal>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
            <literal>groupN</literal>
        </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
    <para>
      These attribute names should be delimited by (an arbitrary number
      of) whitespace characters. Note that <varname>timestamp</varname>
      and <varname>message</varname> derive from the logging event, while
      <varname>host</varname>, <varname>domain</varname> and
      <varname>service</varname> are properties added to the event's
      diagnostic context map.
    </para>
    <para>
      The key field name <varname>groupN</varname>, where
      <literal>N</literal> is an integer, means that the
      <literal>Nth</literal> substring (specified by parentheses) will
      be included.  For <literal>N=0</literal>, <varname>group0</varname>
      is identical to <literal>message</literal>, which means that the whole
      message string should be included as an identifier.
    </para>
    <para>
    Alarms that are generated by the code at the origin of the problem
    may carry with them other arbitrary unique identifier values, but custom
    definitions are limited to the values associated with these fixed fields.
    </para>
    </section>
    <section id="cf-alarms-prop">
    <title>Miscellaneous Properties of the &serv-alarms; Service</title>
    <para>
       There are a number of other settings avaible for customization;
       check the files
	   <filename>&path-ods-usd;/alarms.properties</filename> and
	   <filename>&path-ods-usd;/httpd.properties</filename> for the complete list
       with explanations.
    </para>
    </section>
</chapter>
