<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % sharedents SYSTEM "shared-entities.xml" >
%sharedents;
]>


<chapter id="cf-webadmin">

  <title>&dcache; Webadmin Interface</title>

  <para>
    This part describes how to configure the &serv-webadmin; service which runs inside the &domain-http;
    and offers additional features to admins like sending admin-commands equal to those of admin interface (CLI) to chosen cells or displaying billing plots.
  </para>

  <para>
	For authentication and authorisation it offers usage of username/password (currently the kpwd-Plugin)
	or grid certificate talking to &cell-gplazma2;. It also offers a non-authenticated read-only mode.
  </para>

  <para>
	If you are logged in as admin it is possible to send a command to multiple pools or
	a whole	poolgroup in one go. It is even possible to send a command to any &dcache; cell.
	Also, there is information like their size, their id and used space on linkgroups and spacetokens available.
  </para>

  <para>
	From the technical point of view the &serv-webadmin; service uses a Jetty-Server which is embedded in an ordinary &cell-httpd; cell.
	It is using apache-wicket (a webfrontend-framework) and <abbrev>YAML</abbrev> (a CSS-Template Framework).
  </para>
  <section id="cf-webadmin-install">
    <title>Installation</title>
    <para>
      For the authenticated mode a configured &cell-gplazma; is
      required (see also <xref linkend="cf-gplazma-webadmin-example"/>). The user may either authenticate by presenting his grid certificate or
      by entering a valid username/password combination. This way it is possible to login even if the user does not have a grid certificate.
      For a non-authenticated &serv-webadmin; service you just need to start the &cell-httpd; service.
    </para>
    <para>
      For the authenticated mode using a grid certificate the host certificate has to be imported into the &dcache;-keystore.
      In the grid world host certificates are usually signed by national Grid-CAs. Refer to
      the documentation provided by the Grid-CA to find out how to request a certificate. To
      import them into the &dcache;-keystore use this command:
      <screen>&prompt-root; <userinput>&path-odb-n-s;dcache import hostcert</userinput></screen>
      Now you have to initialise your truststore (this is the certificate-store used
      for the SSL connections) by using this command:
      <screen>&prompt-root; <userinput>&path-odb-n-s;dcache import cacerts</userinput></screen>
      The &serv-webadmin; service uses the same truststore as &serv-webdav; service, so you can skip this step if you have &serv-webdav; configured with SSL.
    </para>

    <para>
      Since the &serv-webadmin; service runs inside the &serv-httpd; service you need to enable the httpdDomain in your layout file.
    </para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>[httpdDomain]
webadminDCacheInstanceName=coolName</programlisting>
    </informalexample>

    <para>
      The default instance name is the name of the host which runs the httpdDomain and the default http port number is  <literal>2288</literal> (this is the default port number of the &serv-httpd; service).
      Now you should be able to have a read-only access to the webpage  <uri>http://example.com:2288/webadmin</uri>.

      The next step will explain setting for the authenticated mode.
      The default value for the <varname>webadminHttpsPort</varname>
      is <literal>8444</literal>. In the following example we will enable the authenticated mode and define the  <varname>webadminAdminGid</varname>.
    </para>
    <informalexample>
      <programlisting>[httpdDomain]
webadminDCacheInstanceName=coolName
authenticated=true
webadminAdminGid=1000</programlisting>
    </informalexample>

	<para>
	  The most important value is <varname>webadminAdminGid</varname>, because it configures who is allowed to
	  alter &dcache; behaviour, which certainly should not be everyone:
	  <programlisting>#
#   When a user has this GID he can become an Admin for the webadmin interface
#
webadminAdminGid=1000</programlisting>
      To see all webadmin specific property values have a look at
      <filename>&path-ods-usd;/defaults/httpd.properties</filename>.

	  For information on &cell-gplazma; configuration have a look at
      <xref linkend="cf-gplazma"/> and for a special example
      <xref linkend="cf-gplazma-webadmin-example"/>.

      After startup of the httpdDomain you can reach the Webadmin in authenticated mode by <uri>https://example.com:8444/webadmin</uri>.
      You will be asked to login as admin.
    </para>
  </section>

</chapter>