<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % sharedents SYSTEM "shared-entities.xml" >
%sharedents;
<!ENTITY dn "<acronym>DN</acronym>">
<!ENTITY fqan "<acronym>FQAN</acronym>">
]>


<chapter id="cf-stage-protection">

  <title>
    Stage Protection
  </title>

  <chapterinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Irina</firstname>
      <surname>Kozlova</surname>
    </author>
  </chapterinfo>

  <para>
    Initially &dcache; has been designed to be a disk cache in front of a Tape Storage System,
    moving files onto the tape-backend and restoring them when needed. Those operations are
    handled transparently to the user. The downside of this approach is that a simple read of
    a file, not being on disk, automatically triggers a tape operation. As tape operations are
    expensive and may interfere with storing raw data, coming from the Tier 0, this feature
    had to be reviewed. As a result, it has been agreed with the experiments that only a production
    user should be allowed to trigger such a tape operation. &dcache; is now implementing a first version
    of such a protective mechanism.
  </para>

  <para>
    A &dcache; system administrator may specify a list of &dn;s/&fqan;s which are
    allowed to trigger tape read accesses for files not being available on disk. Users, requesting
    tape-only files, and not being on that <firstterm>white list</firstterm>, will receive a permission
    error and no tape operation is launched. In 1.9.5-20 release, stage protection
    can be enhanced to allow authorization specific to a &dcache; storage group. The additional
    configuration parameter is optional allowing the stage protection to be backwards compatible
    when stage authorization is not specific to a storage group.
   </para>

  <section id="cf-stage-protection-configuration">
    <title>Configuration of Stage Protection</title>

  <para>
  In the 1.9.4 series, stage protection had to be configured in every door and in the &cell-pinmngr;.
  Starting with the 1.9.5 series, stage protection can optionally be configured in the &cell-poolmngr;
  rather than on the doors and &cell-pinmngr;. Thus the white list needs to be present
  on a single node only. To enable this, define the following parameter in <filename>config/dCacheSetup</filename>:
  </para>

  <programlisting>stagePolicyEnforcementPoint=PoolManager</programlisting>

  <para>
  The file name of the white list must be configured by setting the
  <varname>stageConfigurationFilePath</varname> parameter in <filename>config/dCacheSetup</filename>:
  </para>

  <programlisting>stageConfigurationFilePath=${ourHomeDir}/config/StageConfiguration.conf</programlisting>

  <para>
  The parameter only needs to be defined on the nodes which enforce the stage protection;
  i.e., either on the doors and &cell-pinmngr;, or in &cell-poolmngr;.
  </para>

  </section>

  <section id="cf-stage-protection-whiteList">
  <title>Definition of the White List</title>

  <para>
  The Stage Configuration File will contain a white list.
  Each line of the white list may contain one or two regular expressions
  enclosed in double quotes. The first regular expression matches the &dn;,
  and the second matches the &fqan; :
  </para>
      <cmdsynopsis>
    <arg choice='plain'>"<replaceable>DN</replaceable>"</arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>"<replaceable>FQAN</replaceable>"</arg>
      </cmdsynopsis>

    <para>
   Lines starting with a hash symbol <literal>#</literal> are discarded as comments.
   </para>

   <para>
   The regular expression syntax follows the syntax defined for the
  <ulink url="http://java.sun.com/javase/6/docs/api/java/util/regex/Pattern.html">
    Java Pattern class </ulink>.
  </para>

  <para>
    Here are some examples of the White List Records for the 1.9.5 series:
  </para>

  <programlisting>".*" "/atlas/Role=production"
"/C=DE/O=DESY/CN=Kermit the frog"
"/C=DE/O=DESY/CN=Beaker" "/desy"
"/O=GermanGrid/.*" "/desy/Role=.*"</programlisting>
  <para>
    This example authorizes a number of different groups of users:
  </para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      Any user with the <phrase xml:space='preserve'>&fqan; <literal>/atlas/Role=production</literal></phrase>.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      The user with the <phrase xml:space='preserve'>&dn; <literal>/C=DE/O=DESY/CN=Kermit the frog</literal></phrase>, irrespective
      of which VOMS groups he belongs to.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      The user with the <phrase xml:space='preserve'>&dn; <literal>/C=DE/O=DESY/CN=Beaker</literal></phrase> but only if he is
      also identified as a member of VO <literal>desy</literal>
      (<phrase xml:space='preserve'>&fqan; <literal>/desy</literal></phrase>)
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      Any user with &dn; and &fqan; that match <literal>/O=GermanGrid/.*</literal> and <literal>/atlas/Role=.*</literal>
      respectively.
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>With the plain &dcap; protocol the &dn; and &fqan; are not known for any users.
    Therefore, there is a special case for &dcap; users in 1.9.5. In order to allow all &dcap; users
    to stage files the white list should contain the following record:
  </para>
  <programlisting>"Unknown" "nobody"</programlisting>

  <para>If this line is commented or not present in the white list,
  all &dcap; users will be disallowed to stage files.
  </para>

<section id="cf-stage-protection-whiteListStorageGroup">
  <title>Authorizing Only Certain Storage Groups</title>
  <para>
  In 1.9.5-20 release, an optional storage group parameter can be specified.
  Each line of the white list may contain up to three regular
  expressions enclosed in double quotes.
  The regular expressions match the &dn;, &fqan;, and Storage Group written in the following format:
  </para>

      <cmdsynopsis>
    <arg choice='plain'>"<replaceable>DN</replaceable>"</arg>
    <arg choice='opt'>"<replaceable>FQAN</replaceable>"
    <arg choice='opt'>"<replaceable>StorageGroup</replaceable>"</arg>
    </arg>
      </cmdsynopsis>

  <para>
    If a storage group is specified all three parameters must be provided.
    The regular expression <literal>".*"</literal> may be used to authorize any &dn;
    or any &fqan;. Consider the following example:
   </para>

    <programlisting>".*" "/atlas/Role=production" "h1:raw@osm"
"/C=DE/O=DESY/CN=Scooter" ".*" "sql:chimera@osm"</programlisting>

  <para>
  In the example above:
  </para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      Any user with <phrase xml:space='preserve'>&fqan; <literal>/atlas/Role=production</literal></phrase>
      is allowed to stage files located in the storage group <literal>h1:raw@osm</literal>.
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      The user <literal>/C=DE/O=DESY/CN=Scooter</literal>, irrespective of which VOMS groups he belongs to,
      is allowed to stage files located in the storage group <literal>sql:chimera@osm</literal>.
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>In the following example, all &dcap; users are allowed to stage files located
  in the storage group <literal>h1:raw@osm</literal>:
  </para>
  <programlisting>"Unknown" "nobody" "h1:raw@osm"</programlisting>
 </section>
</section>

</chapter>