<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">     

<chapter id="cf-repman">
  <title>Resilience with the Replica Manager</title>
  
  <authorblurb>
    <simpara>Alex Kulyavtsev</simpara>
    <simpara>Mathias de Riese</simpara>
  </authorblurb>

  <para>
    If no <glossterm linkend="gl-tss">tertiary storage
    system</glossterm> is connected to a <dcache/> instance (i.e. it
    is configured as a <glossterm linkend="gl-lfs">large file
    store</glossterm>), there might be only one copy of each file on
    disk. (At least the <glossterm linkend="gl-precious">precious
    replica</glossterm>.) If a higher security and/or availability is
    required, the resilience feature of <dcache/> can be used: If
    running in the default configuration, the replica manager will
    make shure that the number of <glossterm
    linkend="gl-replica">replicas</glossterm> of a file will be at
    least 2 and not more than 3. If only one replica is present it
    will be copied to another pool by a <glossterm
    linkend="gl-p2p">pool to pool transfer</glossterm>. If 4 or more
    replicas exist, some of them will be deleted.
  </para>

  <section id="cf-repman-start">
    <title>Starting the Replica Manager</title>

    <para>
      Beginning with version 1.6.6 of <dcache/> the replica manager
      can be started as follows:
    </para>

    <para>
      The replica manager will use the same postgresql database and
      database user <literal>srmdcache</literal> as the <srm/>. The
      standard configuration assumes that the database server is
      installed on the same machine as the replica manager - usually
      the admin node of the <dcache/> instance. To create and
      configure the database <literal>replicas</literal> used by the
      replica manager in the database server do:

<screen><rootprompt/>su postgres
<userprompt/>createdb -O srmdcache replicas
<userprompt/>psql -h localhost -U srmdcache -d replicas -f /opt/d-cache/etc/pd_dump-s-U_enstore.sql
<userprompt/>exit</screen>
      
    </para>

    <para>
      The start-up script <filename>bin/dcache-core</filename> already
      contains the correct lines to start and stop the domain
      containing the replica manager as comments. Just remove the two
      hash (<quote>#</quote>) signs and restart the <dcache/> instance.
      The replica manager may also be started separately by 

<screen><rootprompt/>/opt/d-cache/jobs/replica -logfile=/opt/d-cache/log/replica.log start</screen>

      and stopped by

<screen><rootprompt/>/opt/d-cache/jobs/replica stop</screen>

    </para>

    <para>
      In the default configuration, all pools of the <dcache/>
      instance will be managed. The replica manager will keep the
      number of replicas between 2 and 3 (including). At each restart
      of the replica manager the pool configuration in the database
      will be recreated.
    </para>

  </section> 

  <section>
    <title>Operation</title>

    

  </section>

</chapter>
