<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN"
                         "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % sharedents SYSTEM "shared-entities.xml" >
%sharedents;
]>


<chapter id="cf-webadmin">

  <title>&dcache; Webadmin-Interface</title>

  <chapterinfo>
    <author>
      <firstname>Jan</firstname>
      <surname>Schaefer</surname>
    </author>
  </chapterinfo>

  <para>
    This part describes how to configure the &cell-webadmin;-interface which
    is a replacement for the old &cell-httpd;-service and offers additional
    features to act as an adminservice to admins.
  </para>


  <para>
	The &cell-webadmin;-interface uses a Jetty-Server which is embedded in an odinary &dcache;-cell.
	It is using apache-wicket (a webfrontend-framework) and <abbrev>YAML</abbrev> (a CSS-Template Framework).
	The application is wired up by a Spring IOC-Container. It receives the information from
	&dcache; infoservice as &xml; which are parsed and presented. For authentication and
	authorisation it offers usage of username/password(currently KAuth-File) or
	the grid-certificate talking to &cell-gplazma;. It also offers a non-authenticated,
	read-only mode.
  </para>

  <para>
	If you are logged in as admin it is possible to send a command to multiple pools or
	a whole	poolgroup in one go. It is even possible to send a command to any &dcache;-Cell.
  </para>

  <section id="cf-webadmin-install">
    <title>Installation</title>
    <para>
      To enable your &dcache; to run the &cell-webadmin;-interface your system has to run
      the &cell-info; service. For the authenticated mode a configured &cell-gplazma; is also
      required. The KAuth-File has to be on the same machine then the &cell-webadmin; for
      this to work. For a non-authenticated &cell-webadmin; you just need to give the &cell-webadmin;
      service to a domain and maybe configure the port &cell-webadmin; will listen on
	<varname>webadminHttpPort</varname>.
    </para>
    <para>
      For authenticated mode a host certificate has to be imported into the &dcache;-keystore.
      In the grid world host certificates are usually signed by national Grid-CAs. Refer to
      the documentation provided by the Grid-CA to find out how to request a certificate. To
      import them into the &dcache;-keystore use this command:
      <screen>&prompt-root; <userinput>/opt/d-cache/bin/dcache import hostcert</userinput></screen>
      Now you have to initialise your truststore (this is the certificate-store used
      for the SSL connections) by using this command:
      <screen>&prompt-root; <userinput>/opt/d-cache/bin/dcache import cacerts</userinput></screen>
      Webadmin-interface uses the same truststore as &cell-webDAV;, so maybe you can skip
      this step.
    </para>
    <para>
You can enable the &cell-webadmin; interface by adding the service (&cell-webadmin;) to a domain;
for example:
      <programlisting>[webadminDomain]
[webadminDomain/webadmin]
webadminHttpsPort=8443
webadminHttpPort=8080
webadminDCacheInstanceName=coolName
webadminAuthenticated=true
webadminAdminGid=1000</programlisting>
	</para>
	<para>
	  The most important value is <varname>webadminAdminGid</varname>, because it configures who is allowed to
	  alter dCache behaviour, which certainly should not be everyone:
	  <programlisting>#  ---- GID a user has to have to be considered an Admin of webadmininterface
#
#   When a user has this GID he can become an Admin for webadmininterface
webadminAdminGid=1000</programlisting>
      To see all webadmin specific property values have a look at
      <filename>${dcache.home}/share/defaults/webadmin.properties</filename>

	  For information on &cell-gplazma; configuration have a look at
      <xref linkend="cf-gplazma"/> and for a special example
      <xref linkend="cf-gplazma-webadmin-example"/>.

      After startup of webadmin you can reach it via <uri>http://example.com:8080/webadmin</uri>.
      Since webadmin bases on the &cell-info; it takes some time until all values are populated,
      because &cell-info; needs to collect them first. We are working on making this process
      faster in future releases. It is recommended to let &cell-info; run on the same machine then
      &cell-webadmin;.
    </para>
  </section>

</chapter>
