<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">     

<chapter id="cb-adv">
  <title>Advanced Tuning</title>
  
  <para>
    The use cases described in this chapter are only relevant for
    large-scale dCache Instances which require special tuning
    according to a longer experience with client behaviour.
  </para>
  
  <section id="cb-adv-multi-mover-queues">
    <title>Multiple Queues for Movers in each Pool</title>
    
    
    <section id="cb-adv-multi-mover-queues-d">
      <title>Description</title>
      
      <para>
        Client requests to a dCache system may have rather diverse
        bahaviour. Sometimes it is possible to classify them into
        several typical usage patterns. An example are the following
        two usage patterns: 

        <example>
          <title>To Concurrent Usage Patterns</title>

          <para>
            Data is copied with a high transfer rate to the dCache
            system from an external source. This is done via the
            GridFTP protocol. At the same time batch jobs on a local
            farm process data. Since they only need a small part of
            each file, they use the dCap protocol via the dCap
            library and seek to the position in the file they are
            interested in, read a few bytes, do a few hours of
            calculations, and finally read some more data.
          </para>

        </example>

        As long as the number of active requests do not exceed the
        maximum number of allowed active requests, the two types of
        requests are processed concurrently. The GridFTP transfers
        complete at a high rate while the processing jobs take hours
        to finish. This maximum number of allowed requests is set
        with <cellcommandref linkend="cmd-mover_set_max_active"/>
        and should be tuned according to capabilities of the pool
        host.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        However, if requests are queued, the slow processing jobs
        might clog up the queue and not let the fast GridFTP request
        through, even though the pool just sits there waiting for
        the processing jobs to request more data. While this could
        be temporarily remedied by setting the maximum active
        requests to a higher value, then in turn GridFTP request
        would put a very high load on the pool host.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The above example is pretty realistic: As a rule of thumb,
        GridFTP requests are fastest, dCap requests with the
        <command>dccp</command> program are a little slower and dCap
        requests with the dCap library are very slow. However, the
        usage patterns might be different at other sites and also
        might change over time.
      </para>

    </section>
    
    <section id="cb-adv-multi-mover-queues-s">
      <title>Solution</title>
      
      <para>
        Use separate queues for the movers, depending on the door
        initiating them. This easily allows for a separation of
        requests of separate protocols. Up to 10 mover queues for
        client transfers are available since dCache version
        1.6.6. Earlier versions support only one queue. (Transfers
        from an to a <glossterm linkend="gl-tape_backend">tape
	  backend</glossterm> and <glossterm
	  linkend="gl-p2p">pool-to-pool transfers</glossterm> are
        handled by separate queues, one for each of these transfers.)
      </para>
      
      <para>
        A finer grained queue selection mechanism based on, e.g. the
        IP of the client or the file which has been requested, is
        not possible with this mechanism. However, the <glossterm
	  linkend="gl-pm-comp-psu">pool selection unit
	  (PSU)</glossterm> may provide a separation onto separate
        pools using those criteria.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        In the above example, two separate queues for fast GridFTP
        transfers and slow dCap library access would solve the
        problem. The maximum number of active movers for the GridFTP
        queue should be set to a lower value compared to the dCap
        queue since the fast GridFTP transfers will put a high load
        on the system while the dCap requests will be mostly idle.
      </para>

    </section>
    
    <section id="cb-adv-multi-mover-queues-c">
      <title>Configuration</title>
      
      <para>
        For a multi mover queue setup, the pools have to be told to
        start several queues and the doors have to be configured to
        use one of these. It makes sense to create the same queues
        on all pools. This is done by the following change to the
        <filename>config/pool.batch</filename> file:
        
        <example>
          <title>Modified <filename>config/pool.batch</filename> file for
multiple mover queues</title>
          
<programlisting>...
define context startPools endDefine
  create diskCacheV111.pools.MultiProtocolPool2 ${0} \
         "!MoverMap \
         ${1} \
         <emphasis>-io-queues=<replaceable>queueName-1</replaceable>[,<replaceable>queueName-2</replaceable>[,...,<replaceable>queueName-10</replaceable>]] \</emphasis>
         -recover-control=yes \
         -version=4 \
         -sticky=allowed \
         -sendHitInfoMessages=yes \
         -${2} -${3} -${4} -${5} -${6} -${7} -${8} \
         "
endDefine
...</programlisting>

        </example>
        
        The same can be achived by appending
        <literal>-io-queues=<replaceable>queueName-1</replaceable>,...,<replaceable>queueName-n</replaceable></literal>
        to each line in the <glossterm
	  linkend="gl-poollist-file"><literal>poollist</literal>
	  file</glossterm>. However, this only makes sense if the
        pools should not all have the same queues.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The first in this list of queues
        (<literal><replaceable>queueName-1</replaceable></literal>)
        is the <glossterm linkend="gl-default-mover-queue">default
	  mover queue</glossterm>. Transfers not requesting a
        particular mover queue or requesting a mover queue not
        existing on the selected pool, are handled by this default
        queue.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The pool cell commands <cellcommandref
	  linkend="cmd-mover_ls"/> and <cellcommandref
	  linkend="cmd-mover_set_max_active"/> have an
        <option>-queue</option> option to select the mover queue to
        operate on. Without this option, <cellcommandref
	  linkend="cmd-mover_set_max_active"/> will act on the default
        queue while <cellcommandref linkend="cmd-mover_ls"/> will
        list the requests of all pools for backward compatibility.
      </para>
      
      <para>
        Each door may be configured to use a particular mover
        queue. The pool, selected for this request, doesn't depend
        on the selected mover queue. So a request may go to a pool
        which doesn't have the particular mover queue configured and
        will consequently end up in the default mover queue of that
        pool. 
      </para>
      
      <para>
        The doors are configured to use a particular mover queue as
        in the following example:

        <example>
          <title>Batch file for a GridFTP door using a mover queue</title>
          
<programlisting>...
create dmg.cells.services.login.LoginManager GFTP \
       "<replaceable>portName</replaceable> \
       diskCacheV111.doors.GsiFtpDoorV1 \
       <emphasis>-io-queue=<replaceable>queueName</replaceable> \</emphasis>
       ... \
"</programlisting>
          
        </example>

        All requests send from this door will ask to be scheduled to
        the given mover queue. The selection of the pool is not
        affected.
      </para>

      <para>
        For the dCap protocol, the corresponding door may be
        configured to allow the client to determine the mover queue
        name. In that case the client may use the extra option
        facility to specify a mover queue. Whether the the dCap door
        allows the client to request a particular mover queue or not
        is configured with the
        <option>-io-queue={allowed|denied}</option> option as in the
        following example:

        <example>
          <title>Batch file for a dCap door for allowing the client to select
the mover queue</title>
	    
<programlisting>...
create dmg.cells.services.login.LoginManager DCap \
       "${dCapPort} \
       diskCacheV111.doors.DCapDoor \
       -io-queue=<replaceable>queueName</replaceable> \
       <emphasis>-io-queue-overwrite=allowed \</emphasis>
       ... \
"</programlisting>

        </example>
        
        With the <command>dccp </command> command the queue can now
        be specified as follows: 
        
<screen>dccp -X-io-queue=queueName <replaceable>source</replaceable> <replaceable>destination</replaceable></screen> 
        
        Since <command>dccp</command> requests may be quite
        different from other requests with the dCap protocol, this
        feature may be used to use separate queues for
        <command>dccp</command> requests and other dCap library
        requests. Therefore, the <command>dccp</command> command may
        me changed in future releases to request a special
        <command>dccp</command>-queue by default.
      </para>
      
    </section>
    
  </section>
  <section id="cb-tuning-parameters">
    <title>Tunable Parameters</title>
    
    
    <section id="cb-tuning-parameters-gsiftp">
      <title>gridftp</title>
      <blockquote>
      <table tabstyle="cellattributes">
        <title>Protocol Overview</title>

        <tgroup cols="3" align="center">
          <colspec colnum="1" colname="Variable" colwidth="70"/>
          <colspec colnum="2" colname="Default Value" colwidth="70"/>
          <colspec colnum="3" colname="Description" colwidth="120"/>
          <thead>
             <row><entry>Variable</entry><entry>Default Value</entry><entry>Description</entry></row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row><entry>gsiFtpPortNumber</entry><entry>2811</entry><entry>gsi ftp port listen port</entry></row>
            <row><entry>spaceReservation</entry><entry>false</entry><entry>Use the space reservation service</entry></row>
            <row><entry>spaceReservationStrict</entry><entry>false</entry><entry>Use the space reservation service</entry></row>
            <row><entry>performanceMarkerPeriod</entry><entry>180</entry><entry>Performance markers in seconds</entry></row>
            <row><entry>gplazmaPolicy</entry><entry>${ourHomeDir}/etc/dcachesrm-gplazma.policy</entry><entry>Location of the gPlazma Policy File</entry></row>
            <row><entry>useGPlazmaAuthorizationModule</entry><entry>true</entry><entry>Use the gPlazma module</entry></row>
            <row><entry>useGPlazmaAuthorizationCell</entry><entry>false</entry><entry>Use the gPlazma cell</entry></row>
            <row><entry>gsiftpPoolManagerTimeout</entry><entry>5400</entry><entry>Pool Manager timeout in seconds</entry></row>
            <row><entry>gsiftpPoolTimeout</entry><entry>600</entry><entry>Pool timeout in seconds</entry></row>
            <row><entry>gsiftpPnfsTimeout</entry><entry>300</entry><entry>Pnfs timeout in seconds</entry></row>
            <row><entry>gsiftpMaxRetries</entry><entry>80</entry><entry>Number of PUT/GET retries</entry></row>
            <row><entry>gsiftpMaxStreamsPerClient</entry><entry>10</entry><entry>Number of parallel streams per ftp PUT/GET</entry></row>
            <row><entry>gsiftpDeleteOnConnectionClosed</entry><entry>true</entry><entry>Delete file on connection closed</entry></row>
            <row><entry>gsiftpMaxLogin</entry><entry>100</entry><entry>Maximum number of concurrently logged in users</entry></row>
            <row><entry>clientDataPortRange</entry><entry>20000:25000</entry><entry>The client data port range</entry></row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      </blockquote>
    </section>
  </section>
</chapter>
